Finding aid for University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals (University of Michigan) Records, 1979-2003 0728 Bimu 2
Bentley Historical Library
University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals (University of Michigan) records
1979-2003
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals.
0728 Bimu 2
8.7 linear feet
The University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals (UCUCA) records consist of meeting minutes and agendas, annual reports, and animal facility inspections. The UCUCA works to ensure that all projects using animals at the University of Michigan are conducted in accordance with university guidelines and policies and federal law concerning laboratory animal welfare.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Records were transferred beginning in September 2006 (Donor no. 9789 ).
Accruals
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is restricted under the Executive Officers records policy.
The University of Michigan. University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 1-9
Biographical / Historical
The University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals (UCUCA) was established in 1965 to advise University of Michigan research officials on matters related to the use of animals in research and education. It formed out of the Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine (ULAM) at the Medical School, and was the formal extension of the Animal Care Committee. Combined with the Animal Care Unit, the UCUCA helped to continue the humane treatment of animals regulated by the Laboratory Animal Welfare Act of 1966.
Beginning in 1986, the Committee was required to approve all use of vertebrate animals on campus. Currently, its responsibilities include reviewing applications for the use of animals in research, training, or testing, updating university policies for the treatment of animals, inspecting animal facilities in accordance with these policies, providing training for people working with animals, and advising the Office of the Vice President for Research on matters related to the use of animals in research and education. The Committee also serves to ensure University of Michigan compliance with federal animal welfare regulations through the submittal of reports to the American Association for Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care (AAALAC) the Office of Laboratory Animal Welfare (OLAW), and the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA).
Scope and Contents
The University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals (UCUCA) records consist of meeting minutes and agendas, annual reports and reports of USDA inspections. The records are divided into two series: Meeting Minutes and Agendas and Reports. Within each series, the records are organized in chronological order and retain the original folders and file headings. The records are focused on the administrative activities of the UCUCA.
Animal welfare.; Laboratory animals.; University of Michigan. -- Research.; University of Michigan. Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine.; University of Michigan. University Committee on the Use and Care of Animals.
- Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1979-2003
  Scope and Contents
  The Meeting Minutes and Agendas series (5.5 linear feet, 1979-2003) contains meeting minutes, agendas, and meeting materials. Meetings occur monthly, and these materials provide excellent insight into the management and administration of the UCUCA.
  - Memorandum, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2026
  - 1979-1983 (Box 1)
  - 1984-June 1985 (Box 1)
  - July 1985-December 1985, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1986, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - 1987, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - 1988, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - 1989, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - January 1990-September 1990, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - October 1990-December 1990, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1991, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - 1992, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - 1993, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - January 1994-August 1994, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - September 1994-December 1994, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1995, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - 1996, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - January 1997-April 1997, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - May 1997-December 1997, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - 1998, 11 folders (Box 4)
  - 1999, 12 folders (Box 4)
  - January 2000-July 2000, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - August 2000-December 2000, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 2001, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - 2002, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - January 2003-April 2003, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - May 2003-December 2003, 6 folders (Box 6)
- Reports, 1979-2003
  The Reports series (3.2 linear feet, 1979-2003) consists of reports made by the UCUCA to the University of Michigan Office of the Vice President for Research (OVPR) and federal agencies. Also included are inspection reports of the animal care facilities made by the USDA. The Reports series is an excellent place to find detailed information about the animal care facilities located at the University of Michigan and their functions.
  - American Association for Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care (AAALAC)
    - UCUCA History with, 1979-1983 (Box 6)
    - Annual Report to, 1980-88, 1990-2003; 23 folders (Box 6)
  - Annual Report to the Office of Laboratory Animal Welfare (OLAW), 1986-2002; 17 folders (Box 7)
  - Semi-Annual Report to the Office of the Vice President for Research (OVPR)
    - 1993-1998, 12 folders (Box 7)
    - 1999-2002, 8 folders (Box 8)
    - 2003, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - United States Department of Agriculture (USDA)
    - Annual Report to, 1984-2002; 19 folders (Box 8)
    - Inspection Reports, 1979-1984; 1990-1997; 22 folders (Box 8)